Register of the George Creel Miscellaneous Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
George Creel Miscellaneous Papers
1912-1972
48013
Creel, George, 1876-1953.
4 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, pamphlets, bulletins, clippings, and photographs, relating to American propaganda activities during World War I, and to the Golden Gate International Exposition. Includes publications of the Committee on Public Information. Also includes some papers of Winifred Gay, niece of George Creel, relating to her uncle.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by the Hoover Instituion in 1948.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1876 December 1 Born, Lafayette County, Missouri
1899-1909 Editor, Kansas City Independent
1909-1910 Editor, Denver Post
1911-1913 Editor, Rocky Mountain News
1916 Author, Wilson and the Issues
1917-1919 Chairman, Committee on Public Information
1919 Author, Ireland's Fight For Freedom
1920 Author, How We Advertised America, and The War, The World and Wilson
1926 Author, The People Next Door
1927 Author, Sons of the Eagle
1928 Author, Sam Houston, Colossus in Buckskin
1932 Author, Tom Paine – Liberty Bell
1933 Chairman, San Francisco Regional Labor Board
1935 Chairman, National Advisory Board, Works Progress Administration
1939 U.S. Commissioner, Golden Gate International Exposition
1944 Author, War Criminals
1947 Author, Rebel at Large: Recollections of Fifty Crowded Years
1949 Author, Russia's Race for Asia
1953 October 3 Died, San Francisco
Scope and Content of Collection
The George Creel Miscellaneous Papers, acquired in 1988 and 1994, consist of correspondence, pamphlets, bulletins, clippings, and photographs, relating to American propaganda activities during World War I, and to the Golden Gate International Exposition. Also included are publications of the Committee on Public Information, and papers of Winifred Gay, niece of George Creel, relating to her uncle.
The bulk of the material relates to the Committee on Public Information and consists of George Creel's personal copies of its publications. The Photographs provide a glimpse into his personal life and focus on his tenure as U.S. commissioner, Golden Gate International Exposition. The Speeches and Writings represent only a fragment of Creel's prolific output.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Personal and Family File, Speeches and Writings, United States Committee on Public Information Publications, Photographs, and Memorabilia.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Propaganda, American.; World War, 1914-1918--Propaganda.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.; Golden Gate International Exposition (1939-1940: San Francisco, Calif.); United States. Committee on Public Information.; Gay, Winifred.
Occupations
Journalists.
Container List
- Personal and Family File, 1912-1972. (Box 1)
  Articles, correspondence, and obituary relating to George Creel's personal life and work, arranged in two subgroups, family and personal
  - Family file
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1953 October-November. (Folder 1: 1-2)
        Includes letters of condolence
      - Gay, Winifred (niece), 1942-1968. (Folder 1: 3)
        Includes correspondence with A. C. Wedemeyer
    - Obituaries, 1941-1972 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Personal file
    - Articles about George Creel, 1917-1953 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Correspondence.
      Includes letters from others during his illness
      - Undated (Folder 1: 6)
      - 1912-1953 (Folder 1: 7-9)
    - Office file
      - Chairman, Committee on Public Information, ca. 1917-1967. (Folder 1: 10)
        Includes information relating to a conference, "Fifty Years after George Creel: Progress and Perspectives on America's Role in Public Diplomacy"
      - United States commissioner, Golden Gate International Exposition, 1940 (Fodler 1: 11)
    - Obituary, 1953 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Miscellany, 1966-1968. (Folder 1: 13)
      Includes some financial papers
- Speeches and Writings, 1939-1952.
  Articles, letters to the editor and publisher, statement, and reviews of George Creel's books, arranged chronologically
  - Article fragment, undated. (Folder 1: 14)
    Typescript
  - Chapter on federal participation in the Golden Gate International Exposition, undated. (Folder 1: 15)
  - "Doubts Any Change in Appeasement,", undated. (Folder 1: 16)
    Printed fragment
  - Letters to the editor, including one to the Saturday Review of Literature, undated. (Folder 1: 17)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Letter to the publisher, Yale University Press, 1939 June 23. (Folder 1: 18)
  - Reviews
    - Rebel at Large: Recollections of Fifty Crowded Years, 1947
      - Samuel Hopkins Adams and Joseph Henry Jackson, undated. (Folder 1: 19)
        Printed copy
      - Evening News, 1947 October 30. (Folder 1: 20)
      - New York Sun, 1947 October 31. (Folder 1: 21)
      - Chicago Tribune, Walter Trojan, 1947 November 2. (Folder 1: 22)
      - World Herald, James Keogh, 1947 November 9. (Folder 1: 23)
      - San Francisco Chronicle, Earl C. Behrens, 1947 November 17. (Folder 1: 24)
      - Saturday Review of Literature, John T. Winterich, 1947 November 22(?). (Folder 1: 25)
    - Russia's Race for Asia, Book Talk, Book Talk, edited by John C. Hill, 1949 March, and Human Events, Rosalie M. Gordon, 1961 September 8. (Folder 1: 26)
      Printed copies
  - "Meaty-Mouthed," article, San Francisco Call-Bulletin, 1951 September 5. (Folder 1: 27)
  - Statement [on Democratic Party policy], 1952 May 30. (Folder 1: 28)
- United States Committee on Public Information Publications, 1917-1919. (Box 2)
  Arranged by title of item or series. Some volumes are annotated
  - General
    - The Activities of the Committee on Public Information, 1918 February 3
    - The Kaiserite in America: One Hundred and One German Lies, ca. 1918
    - War Work of Women in Colleges, 1918 January
      Red, White, and Blue series
    - No. 1, How the War Came to America, 1917 June 15
    - No. 2, National Service Handbook, 1917 July 30
    - No. 3, The Battle Line of Democracy: Prose and Poetry of the World War, 1917
    - No. 4, The President's Flag Day Address, with Evidence of Germany's Plans, 1917 September 15
    - No. 5, Conquest and Kultur: Aims of the Germans in Their Own Words, 1918 January
    - No. 6, German War Practices, part I, Treatment of Civilians, 1918 January
    - No. 8, German War Practices, part II, German Treatment of Conquered Territory, 1918 March
    - No. 9, War, Labor, and Peace: Some Recent Addresses and Writings of President Wilson, 1918 March
    - No. 10, German Plots and Intrigues in the United States during the Period of Our Neutrality, 1918 July
  - War Information series
    - No. 1, The War-Message and Facts behind It: Annotated Text of President Wilson's Message, April 2, 1917, 1917 June
    - No. 2, The Nation in Arms, 1917 August
    - No. 11, The German War Code, Contrasted with the War Manuals of the United States, Great Britain, and France, 1918 February
    - No. 12, American and Allied Ideals: An Appeal to Those Who Are Neither Hot Nor Cold, 1918 February
    - No. 13, German Militarism and Its German Critics, Fully Illustrated by Extracts from German Newspapers, 1918 March
    - No. 14, The War for Peace: The Present War as Viewed by Friends of Peace, 1918 March
    - No. 15, Why America Fights Germany, 1918 March
    - No. 16, The Study of the Great War: A Topical Outline, with Extensive Quotations and Reading Reference, 1918 April
    - No. 18, Regimental History of the United States Regular Army: Chronological Outline, 1866-1918, 1918 August
    - No. 19, Lieber and Schurz: Two Loyal Americans of German Birth, 1918 October
    - No. 20, The German-Bolshevik Conspiracy, 1918 October
  - Four Minute Men Bulletin, nos. 1-46, (1917 May 22 – 1918 December 24). (Box 3)
    Two copies. Bound in the same volume are the Four Minute Men Army Bulletins, School Bulletins, and the News
  - Victory Dinner and Dance of the Division of Pictorial Publicity, 1919 February 14.
    Contains a history of the division's work, a chart showing the number of poster designs produced for government and private agencies, a list of poster artists, and reproductions of selected posters with names of artists
- Photographs, 1894-1949. (Box 4)
  89 prints and 11 negatives depicting George Creel, his family, and personalities such as Frank J. Hennessy, J. Edgar Hoover, W. R. Lawson, Frank Murphy, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and others
  - 14 prints depicting George Creel and Blanche Bates Creel (Folder 4: 1)
  - 1 print depicting George Creel's mother with two other ladies and his white bull terrier, Kansas City, Missouri
  - 1 print depicting Hal and Nell(?) Creel, Staten Island
  - 4 prints depicting George Creel, including 1 with his dog, n.d.
  - 1 print depicting George Creel with Frank J. Hennessy and others
  - 2 prints depicting George Creel and others on the occasion of the groundbreaking ceremony of the Federal Theater Building, Treasure Island, San Francisco
  - 3 prints, including 2 depicting George Creel and 1 print of his poem, "A Prayer," illustrated by Malcolm Strauss (Folder 4: 2)
  - 1 print depicting an unidentified building, n.d.
  - 1 print of unidentified individuals at the beach, 1894 (Folder 4: 3)
  - 3 prints, including 2 depicting George Creel on a camel's back in Khartoum, Sudan, and 1 depicting him standing next to a big stone, 1912
  - 1 print depicting George Creel, 1918
  - 7 prints depicting George Creel's family(?), San Francisco, 1924
  - 5 prints depicting George Creel, 1934 and 1937
  - 1 print depicting George Creel with Alice May Rosseter, Treasure Island, San Francisco, 1939
  - 12 prints of the Federal Building under construction at Treasure Island, San Francisco, 1938 (Folder 4: 4)
  - 1 print depicting George Creel, 1938
  - 1 print depicting George Creel and others at the Indian exhibit in the Federal Building, Golden Gate International Exposition, 1939
  - 1 print depicting the Thirtieth Infantry holding U.S. flags, 1939
  - 3 prints of a special event, 1939
  - 1 print depicting Frank Murphy, U.S. attorney general, receiving military honors, 1939
  - 4 prints depicting Edgar Bergen, Charles McCarthy, and Chief Big Turnip(?) on sun deck outside George Creel's office, Federal Building, Treasure Island, San Francisco, 1939 (Folder 4: 5)
  - 1 print of President Franklin D. Roosevelt in a motorcade during his visit to San Francisco(?), 1939
  - 1 print depicting a large group of people at the opening day of the Federal Building(?), 1939
  - 1 print depicting Simon E. Baldwin, governor of Connecticut, in the recreation court of the Federal Building with Joe Gomez, instructor in fly casting, 1939
  - 1 print depicting George Creel with a congressional group, 1939
  - 1 print depicting W. R. Lawson with George Creel in his office, 1939
  - 1 print depicting a group of people observing Bastille Day, 1939 (Folder 4: 6)
  - 1 print depicting George Creel with Herbert B. Maw(?), governor of Utah, 1939
  - 1 print depicting a number of people riding horses with flags in their hands, 1939
  - 1 print of a Fourth of July parade, 1939
  - 1 print depicting George Creel with Frank Murphy and J. Edgar Hoover on sun deck off George Creel's office, 1939 April
  - 1 print of Memorial Day ceremonies, 1939 May
  - 3 prints of the Maharaja of Kapurthala and his son, Amerjit Singh, 1939 May 26
  - 1 print depicting George Creel with Rene d'Harnoncourt and Mr. and Mrs. Lewis O. Barrows, 1939 July 20 (Folder 4: 7)
  - 5 prints of George Creel's office in the Federal Building, Treasure Island, San Francisco, 1939-1940
  - 1 print of George Creel, 1940 July 3
  - 1 print of Alice Rosseter Creel, 1943
  - 2 prints of George Creel, 1949 January
  - 11 negatives, undated (Folder 4: 8)
- Memorabilia, ca. 1939.
  A silver-colored tray made from a printing plate
  - A silver-colored tray made from the printing plate for George Creel and Alice May Rosetter's wedding announcement (Folder 4: 9)